In this last discussion, in order to close off the chapter,
we're gonna cover both cardiomyopathy and cardiac tumors.
Cardiomyopathy refers to myocardial diseases
that result in cardiac dysfunction.
The first is called dilated cardiomyopathy.
In this particular case, you get dilatation
of all four chambers of the heart.
This is the most common form of cardiomyopathy.
Here's what it looks like.
You get massively dilated chambers of the heart.
You can look at the two atria here,
and you can look at the two ventricles here.
Now, the problem with this is that it's gonna result
in a systolic dysfunction.
If you stretch the heart so that it's no longer able
to contract properly, that massive stretching of the heart
is then going to result in a problem with systole,
so that you won't be able to empty the heart.
And, of course, that's gonna result
in biventricular congestive heart failure.
Both the left and the right sides
are both going to fail together.
The complications include mitral
and tricuspid valve regurgitation.
Imagine that if this is the heart here,
and you've got the right atrium, right ventricle,
left atrium, left ventricle.
As you stretch this heart, you're going to be stretching
the mitral valve and the tricuspid valve.
Again, this is the tricuspid.
And then you'll stretch the mitral valve.
And again, that stretching is gonna result
in regurgitation of those valves.
So, number one, you get systolic dysfunction.
And number two, you're gonna get stretching
and regurgitation of these valves.
Another complication would be arrhythmia.
The way I think about this is that as you stretch the heart,
you're also stretching the conduction systems of the heart.
And so you're gonna start getting funny conductions
across that system, giving you arrhythmias.
Now, most commonly, dilated cardiomyopathy
is idiopathic.
We don't know the cause.
But some very high-yield causes to be aware of
include genetic mutations.
Usually, the most common genetic mutation
would be autosomal dominant.
Myocarditis can do it.
The most common bug to cause myocarditis
would be Coxsackievirus.
That results in a lymphocytic infiltrate in the myocardium.
The patients get chest pain.
They can get arrhythmia with sudden death.
They can get heart failure.
If they manage to survive the myocarditis,
then one of the late complications
is dilated cardiomyopathy.
Alcohol abuse, very high-yield,
can cause a dilated cardiomyopathy.
There are some drugs that can cause it.
For example, doxorubicin can result
in a dilated cardiomyopathy, and so can cocaine.
And then finally, particularly high-yield, is pregnancy.
Women who are pregnant either late in the third trimester
or, for example, soon after birth
can develop heart failure due to a dilated cardiomyopathy.
Now, here's a picture of myocarditis
just to remind you of myocarditis
as a cause of dilated cardiomyopathy.
You can see all the lymphocytes present
within the myocardium.
Again, myocarditis, most common cause, Coxsackievirus.
And this can result in death during the acute phase,
or if the patient survived, can eventually result
in a dilated cardiomyopathy.
Now, the treatment for dilated cardiomyopathy
is transplant.
There's no way to fix that dilated heart.
Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy is when you get
massive hypertrophy of the left ventricle.
The most common cause, and of course, very high-yield,
is that you get genetic mutations
in the sarcomere proteins, high-yield,
most commonly autosomal dominant.
Now, these patients are gonna get
decreased cardiac output.
And the reason is because the hypertrophy
makes the heart wall so tight
that you can't fill the heart anymore.
Basically, the wall becomes so full of muscle
that you lose compliance.
And so you get a diastolic dysfunction
where you can't fill the heart.
At the same time, the patients can get sudden death
due to ventricular arrhythmias.
This is the most common cause of sudden death
in young athletes, and we're all aware
of those athletes that are playing on the field
and all of a sudden pass out.
And that's classically due
to a hypertrophic cardiomyopathy.
Another complication is syncope with exercise.
We can illustrate that very quickly.
Right atrium, right ventricle,
left atrium, left ventricle.
And the idea here is that you get
this preferential involvement
of the intraventricular septum
right beneath the aortic valve.
Now, this is basically going to create
almost like a relative block,
the same way that aortic stenosis
would create a block.
This would create a relative block
so that you wouldn't be able to get
blood across this very well.
And that would then present with syncope
during exercise.
So that's basically,
you get a functional aortic stenosis.
Now, if biopsy were performed,
you would see myofiber hypertrophy
with disarray.
And this is a particularly high-yield image,
so let me just take you through it.
Normally, when you look at the myocytes,
they should all sort of be lined up very nicely
and in parallel.
However, notice here that there's all this
disorganization with the myocytes
sort of going in every different direction.
And that's called myocyte disarray.
And it's the classic finding
in hypertrophic cardiomyopathy.
Restrictive cardiomyopathy is when you are restricted
from filling the heart.
And that's because there's a decreased compliance
of the ventricular endomyocardium.
Again, you can't fill,
so there'll be a diastolic problem.
Now, what are the causes?
Amyloid can fill the heart,
making the heart very difficult to expand.
And so, therefore, that would result
in a restrictive cardiomyopathy.
Sarcoidosis, the granulomas of sarcoidosis
can get into the wall of the heart,
making it difficult to expand,
resulting in a restrictive cardiomyopathy.
Hemochromatosis, if iron gets into the wall of the heart,
it can do the same thing.
There's an interesting disorder
called endocardiofibroelastosis.
And this is when patients have a dense layer
of fibrosis and elastic tissue in the endocardium.
Now, remember that the layers of the heart
are the endocardium, and then the myocardium,
and then the epicardium.
Now, imagine if this endocardium
becomes massively fibrosed
and thickened with elastic tissue.
You won't be able to stretch this
when you expand the heart open,
and so that would then result
in a restrictive cardiomyopathy.
Now, I should note that endocardiofibroelastosis
would classically be seen in children,
and so it's one of the rare causes
of a restrictive cardiomyopathy in children.
Another cause of restrictive cardiomyopathy
is Loeffler syndrome.
The idea here is that you get
an eosinophilic infiltrate with inflammation
within the wall of the heart, again with eosinophils,
and that results in fibrosis of the endomyocardium,
both the endocardium and the myocardium.
Of course, this fibrosis would then make it difficult
for the heart to expand and fill,
and so you'd get a restrictive cardiomyopathy.
Patients with a restrictive cardiomyopathy
will present with congestive heart failure,
and again, that's because they're not able
to fill the heart, so the blood will back up
behind the heart.
And the classic finding on EKG,
because you've got all this material
on the wall of the heart will be low-voltage EKG
with diminished QRS amplitudes,
and that's important to note as well.
The final section of this chapter
deals with cardiac tumors.
It's very straightforward.
The first cardiac tumor is called a myxoma.
This is a mesenchymal proliferation
where you get a gelatinous appearance to the tumor.
On histology, it shows abundant ground substance,
and that's what makes it look so gelatinous,
and this is the most common primary cardiac tumor in adults.
Remember that in adults,
they're not going to be able to produce a tumor,
so the only real tumor of the heart
that you're going to get
is going to be a tumor of the mesenchymal connective tissue.
Again, that's called a myxoma.
Now, this tumor normally grows in the left atrium
as a pedunculated mass,
and it can cause syncope due to obstruction
of the mitral valve.
Let's briefly illustrate this.
Here's a picture of the heart.
Again, these are our four chambers,
and in this particular case,
we're in the left atrium,
and you've got this pedunculated mass.
Pedunculated means it grows off a little stalk.
And so you've got this pedunculated mass.
Now, this mass could easily block the mitral valve here,
and were it to block the mitral valve,
that would block the blood flow through the heart.
Of course, blood would not go to the brain then,
and so you'd get syncope.
And so that's why we say here in the book
that it causes syncope due to obstruction
of the mitral valve.
The next tumor is rhabdomyoma.
Rhabdomyoma means striated muscle,
and oma means mass.
This is a benign hemartoma of cardiac muscle.
It's the most common primary cardiac tumor in children.
High yield, it's associated with tuberous sclerosis.
That is very high yield,
and it usually arises in the ventricle.
Now, the last discussion about cardiac tumors
involves metastases.
Metastases to the heart is more common
than primary tumors.
And common metastases to the heart,
they include breast and lung cancer,
melanoma, and lymphoma.
These are the tumors that love to go to the heart.
When they go to the heart,
they usually go to the pericardium,
and it results in a pericardial effusion.
And so that closes off both the section and this chapter.